{"tossups": [{"question": "Carl Jung used the comparison of Apollo and Dionysus to define one aspect of this concept. Paul Costa and Robert McCrae developed the NEO [N-E-O] test for this concept, and found that different cultures share similar patterns of the \u201cfive-factors\u201d included in that exam. Alfred Adler argued that aspects of this concept are developed to avoid an (*) \u201cinferiority complex,\u201d and it is commonly measured through the \u201cMinnesota Multiphasic Inventory\u201d and the Myers-Briggs Type Indicator. For 10 points, name this psychological concept defined as the set of behaviors of individuals.", "answer": "personality ", "subcategory": "Social Science", "category": "Social Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>personality</u></b>", "acceptable": ["personality"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A subordinate of this person was shot twice and stabbed four times in his office during a murder attempt by Alexander Berkman. This person was inspired by Enoch Pratt to fund the establishment of over 3,000 public libraries, and argued for high estate taxes and significant (*) philanthropy as a response to inequality in \u201cThe Gospel of Wealth.\u201d Henry Clay Frick chaired a company owned by this man, which was sold to J.P. Morgan in 1901 as part of the formation of U.S. Steel. For 10 points, name this American businessman and first namesake of a Pittsburgh university.", "answer": "Andrew Carnegie ", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Andrew <b><u>Carnegie</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Andrew Carnegie"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This artist painted a corked bottle on a table between two men in jackets and hats as part of a series on card players. This artist also painted several portraits of an Italian boy in a red vest, and in a more abstract painting, they depicted a group of nude women under some trees on the shore of a pond in The Large (*) Bathers. Another of his paintings includes a pile of cookies on a plate and a tilted bottle with the title Basket of Apples, while he showed a stack of four skulls in the aptly-titled Pyramid of Skulls. For 10 points, name this French post-Impressionist who painted many still lifes.", "answer": "Paul Cezanne ", "subcategory": "Painting", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "Paul <b><u>Cezanne</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Paul Cezanne"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One leader of these people won the Battle of Cerami in a campaign against the Kalbids in Sicily. The Varangian Guard was composed primarily of these people, while the Rurik dynasty of these people established the Kievan Rus. (*) Rollo, another of these people, was given the Duchy of Normandy by Charles the Simple. The monastery on Lindisfarne was raided by these people, who established a settlement at L\u2019anse Aux Meadows in Newfoundland. For 10 points, name this group of Northern Europeans who traveled as far as Persia and North America, often using longships.", "answer": "Vikings (accept Norsemen or Scandinavians; accept Normans or Varangians before mention) ", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Vikings</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Vikings"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Norsemen or Scandinavians; accept Normans or Varangians before mention"}, {"question": "In one poem, this author described \u201csome we loved\u201d who \u201chave drunk their cup a round or two before / and one by one crept silently to rest.\u201d This author cried out \u201cwake! For the sun, who scattered into flight, the stars before him from the field of night\u201d in a collection in which they ask \u201cwhere leaves the rose of yesterday?\u201d and exclaim \u201cOh (*) Wilderness, were Paradise enow!\u201d In the twelfth entry of that collection by this author, he describes a \u201cbook of verses underneath the bough / a jug of wine, a loaf of bread, and thou.\u201d Edward Fitzgerald translated a series of quatrains by, for 10 points, what Perisan author of the Rubaiyat?", "answer": "Omar Khayyam ", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Omar <b><u>Khayyam</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Omar Khayyam"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "These creatures can be identified from hydrostatic skeletons made of mesoglea, while the scyphozoa and hydrozoa classes of these creatures have tetra-radial symmetry. The green fluorescence protein was first isolated from a species of these creatures, who are the (*) oldest group of multi-organ animals. Cube-shaped medusae lend their name to the \u201cbox\u201d type of these creatures, who use venom capable of killing humans. For 10 points, name these members of the phylum Cnidaria, which have an umbrella-shaped bell above stinging tentacles.", "answer": "jellyfish (or sea jellies; prompt on Medusozoa) ", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>jellyfish</u></b>", "acceptable": ["jellyfish"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or sea jellies; prompt on Medusozoa"}, {"question": "Sekhmet gets drunk and passes out to end one of these events in Egyptian mythology. Cessair leads a group fleeing one of these events in an Irish Catholic myth, while, in the Kalevala, Vainamoinen\u2019s wound leads to another of these events probably borrowed from Ugrian myth. In Mayan myth, many humans made from wood died from one of these events, and (*) Utnapishtim recalls surviving one of these events in the Epic of Gilgamesh. A Chinese legend about a two-generation one of these events may be based on an \u201coutburst\u201d one of these on the Yellow River. For 10 points, name these mythical events in which water covers the known world.", "answer": "great floods (accept floods of blood) ", "subcategory": "Mythology", "category": "Mythology", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>great floods</u></b>", "acceptable": ["great floods"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept floods of blood"}, {"question": "The stipulation \u201cfor madmen only\u201d is used in the title of a manuscript in a novel by this author, whose protagonist meets the saxophonist Pablo and criticizes a bust of Goethe. In another novel by this author, a boy runs away from his father after his mother is bitten by a (*) snake. This author created a character who finds a \u201ctreatise\u201d addressed to him while in a magic shop, while another of his characters meets a ferryman who eventually leads him to enlightenment. For 10 points, name this author, who wrote about Harry Haller in Steppenwolf and Vasudeva in Siddhartha.", "answer": "Hermann Hesse ", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Hermann <b><u>Hesse</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Hermann Hesse"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This functional group can be produced from an aldehyde using the Corey-Fuchs reaction, where a unique Wittig reaction is performed followed by a Fritsch-Buttenberg-Wiechell rearrangement. Lindlar\u2019s catalyst can be used to reduce these compounds, which can also be reduced using the (*) Birch Reduction. Oxymercuration oxidation-reduction reactions performed on this functional group can be used to form a ketone. This functional group has an sp [s-p] hybridization, with one sigma bond and two pi bonds. For 10 points, name this functional group, the simplest of which is acetylene, and which has a carbon-carbon triple bond.", "answer": "alkynes (do not accept or prompt on \u201calkanes\u201d or \u201calkenes\u201d) ", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>alkynes</u></b>", "acceptable": ["alkynes"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "do not accept or prompt on \u201calkanes\u201d or \u201calkenes\u201d"}, {"question": "This instrument joins the recorder, oboe, and violin in the concertino group of Bach\u2019s second Brandenburg Concerto. Respighi\u2019s Pines of Rome includes a \u201csanctus\u201d played by this instrument and ends with six buccine, an old form for this instrument, representing a (*) victorious army. Mahler\u2019s 5th symphony opens with a solo by this instrument, and, in Handel\u2019s Messiah, this instrument plays the only instrumental solo after it is sung that \u201cit shall sound,\u201d evoking the image of a king entering the throne room. For 10 points, name this high-pitched brass instrument, which has three valves.", "answer": "trumpet ", "subcategory": "Music", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>trumpet</u></b>", "acceptable": ["trumpet"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Shellfish restoration is a tactic to reverse eutrophication in these aquatic bodies. Residence time is an important measure of health in these ecosystems, as it impacts both the accumulation of sediment and change in oxygen level. Mix levels of these systems include vertically homogeneous and partially stratified, while in another mix type of this system, dense saltwater forms a (*) \u201cwedge\u201d below a similar wedge of freshwater moving in the opposite direction. Types of this environment include drowned river valleys, fjord-type, and bar-built. For 10 points, name these environments of brackish water usually partly enclosed from open sea.", "answer": "estuary (or estuaries; prompt on brackish water or brackish system before mention) ", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>estuary</u></b>", "acceptable": ["estuary"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or estuaries; prompt on brackish water or brackish system before mention"}, {"question": "In this play, one character goes out in the rain to fetch a cab for his mother and sister, but it is stolen by the lead actress when they disappear. That character sticks her tongue out at her father when he appears to ask for money, and responds \u201cnot bloody likely!\u201d to a question about walking. When her father reappears at the end of this play, that character is caught (*) code-switching, and later announces that she plans on marrying Freddy. Two phonetics experts meet in Covent Garden and make a bet over teaching a flower girl to speak \u201cproperly\u201d in, for 10 points, what George Bernard Shaw play about Henry Higgins, Colonel Pickering, and Eliza Doolittle?", "answer": "Pygmalion ", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Pygmalion</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Pygmalion"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "It\u2019s not in Africa, but this country has a population of wild hippos following the closure of a private zoo. This country\u2019s highest point is Pico Cristobal Colon, though the neighboring Pico Simon Bolivar is just a few feet shorter. This country\u2019s portion of the (*) Andes Mountains is divided into the Cordillera Occidental, the Cordillera Oriental, and the Cordillera Central, and its Guajira Peninsula includes the northernmost point in South America. The Magdalena River enters the Caribbean Sea at this country\u2019s port of Barranquilla, just northeast of Cartagena. For 10 points, name this country with capital Bogota.", "answer": "Republic of Colombia ", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Republic of Colombia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Republic of Colombia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "An official who attempted a coup against this leader was tied to five carriages and torn apart. Attempted assassinations of this ruler included one with a lute weighed down by lead and one with a dagger concealed in a map. This leader purged the Hundred (*) Schools of thought, but likely did not bury Confucian scholars alive. The Lingqu Canal and the construction of the Great Wall were public works ordered by this ruler. Rivers of mercury are believed to be in the mausoleum of this ruler, for whom the Terracotta Army was constructed. For 10 points, name this ruler who ended the Warring States Period to become the first person to rule all of China.", "answer": "Qin Shi Huangdi (or Qin Wang Zheng) ", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Qin Shi Huangdi</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Qin Shi Huangdi"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Qin Wang Zheng"}, {"question": "This person answered his own question with \u201ccontrol\u201d after asking his coach \u201cwhat does government mean to you?\u201d In 2012, while wearing a mask to protect a facial injury, this athlete became the youngest player to score 40 points in a game at Madison Square Garden. This NBA player wore a (*) wig and makeup to look like an old man in a series of PepsiMax commercials later turned into the film Uncle Drew. This player hit the go-ahead 3-pointer with a minute to go in Game 7 of the 2016 NBA Finals, but requested a trade from that LeBron James-led team in 2017. For 10 points, name this point guard for the Cleveland Cavaliers, Boston Celtics, and now the Brooklyn Nets.", "answer": "Kyrie Irving (accept either) ", "subcategory": "Trash", "category": "Trash", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Kyrie Irving</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Kyrie Irving"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept either"}, {"question": "One poem by this author ends by describing \u201cfathers from exile\u201d who \u201cwandered back to their native land\u201d where the ocean \u201canswers the wail of the forest.\u201d In that poem by this author, the title woman falls in love with Gabriel during the expulsion of the (*) Acadians. The title character of another poem by this author is raised in Gitche Gumee by a woman who fell from the \u201cfull moon,\u201d Nokomis, and falls in love with Minnehaha. In another poem, he popularized a man \u201cready to ride on spread the alarm\u201d on \u201cthe eighteenth of April, in seventy-five.\u201d For 10 points, name this poet of Evangeline, The Song of Hiawatha, and \u201cPaul Revere\u2019s Ride.\u201d", "answer": "Henry Wadsworth Longfellow ", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Henry Wadsworth <b><u>Longfellow</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Henry Wadsworth Longfellow"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In an opera set just outside this city, a page is discovered under a chair and then mocked about his future military life in \u201cNon Piu Andrai.\u201d In that opera set near this city, one character is nearly forced to marry Marcellina, who is then revealed as his mother and married to (*) Bartolo, a doctor from this city. In another opera set in this city, one character disguises himself as the student Lindoro and attempts to seduce Rosina. For 10 points, in an opera by Rossini, Count Almaviva asks for assistance from his former servant Figaro, the title \u201cbarber of\u201d what city?", "answer": "Seville ", "subcategory": "Other Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Seville</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Seville"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One leader of this empire justified a usurpation by claiming that the previous emperor was a priest impersonating the rightful leader, who had been secretly assassinated. The pretender Gaumata is depicted in the Behistun Inscription, which was carved by this empire. Another ruler of this empire used camels to win the Battle of (*) Thymbra against Croesus of Lydia, and overthrew the earlier Median Empire. Satraps were provincial governors in this empire, which sacked Athens during its invasion of Greece, but was defeated at Plataea and Salamis. For 10 points, name this empire led by Xerxes, Darius the Great, and Cyrus the Great.", "answer": "Achaemenid Empire (or Persian Empire) ", "subcategory": "Ancient History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Achaemenid Empire</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Achaemenid Empire"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Persian Empire"}, {"question": "Practitioners bow to this religion\u2019s five supreme souls in its Namokar Mantra. The sentient and insentient are two of the seven tattvas of this religion, and the jiva, or soul, is the most important of its six substances, or dravya. This religion\u2019s principle that reality and truth cannot be fully expressed is anekantavada, and it is divided into (*) \u201cwhite-clad\u201d and \u201csky-clad\u201d sects, the latter of whom do not wear or own clothes. This religion was led by 24 tirthankaras, the last of whom was Mahavira. For 10 points, name this South Asian religion whose members adhere to ahimsa, or non-violence.", "answer": "Jainism ", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Jainism</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Jainism"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In one type of these devices, the Lorentz factor times the undulator wavelength, divided by 2 pi times the bending radius, equals the strength parameter of the magnetic wiggler. Q-switching is an alternate option to types of these devices that operate in femtosecond-long bursts, and which are called \u201cmode-locked.\u201d An (*) optical cavity is a common method of providing feedback for these devices, in which energy is \u201cpumped\u201d to the gain medium. Light emitted by these devices is collimated and coherent, allowing it to be focused across longer distances. For 10 points, name these devices that emit light through the stimulated emission of radiation.", "answer": "lasers (or light amplification by stimulated emission of radiation; accept free electron laser) ", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>lasers</u></b>", "acceptable": ["lasers"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or light amplification by stimulated emission of radiation; accept free electron laser"}]}